《哥谭》前情提要
Previously on Gotham...
我听说阿卡姆疯人院放你出来了
I heard they let you out of Arkham.
没错  我正常了
Yes. I'm sane.
我是以利亚·范·达尔
I'm Elijah Van Dahl.
奥斯瓦尔德·科波特
Oh, Oswald Cobblepot.
你是格特鲁德的亲人吗
You're related to Gertrud?
她是我母亲
My mother.
她没告诉我啊
She never told me!
告诉你什么
Told you what?
我有个儿子
That I had a son.
你有家了
You have a home now.
有父亲了
And a father.
快乐的大家庭
A big, happy family.
这是梦吗
Is this a dream?
不是梦  孩子
It's not a dream, my boy.
你回家了
You're home.
你好  平克尼警官
Hello, Officer Pinkney.
我能进去吗
Can I come in?
好啊
Sure.
凶器是一根撬棒
Murder weapon was a crowbar.
上面有你的指纹
Your fingerprints were on it.
我被人陷害了
I was set up!
戈登警探被判有罪
Detective Gordon guilty on all counts.
你怎么能不陪在我们身边
How can you not be with us?
生日
Birthdays...
第一步
and first steps
擦破膝盖
and skinned knees...
你得去别的地方
You need to go somewhere.
开始新生活
Start a new life.
吉姆  别这样  我爱你
Jim, don't do this! I love you!
真对不起
I'm so, so sorry.
我爱你  别这样
I love you! Don't do this!
吉姆
Jim!
起来  快点
On your feet! Let's go!
出来
Step out!
排好
Line it up!
向右转  走
Face right! Walk!
仅供学习  禁止商用  更多影视
登陆www.ZiMuZu.tv
翻译 小胖纸Amy   辰星晓Reginamoon   Silence   DustD
翻译 大K   木浅   小酸奶!   草草   后期 饿得慌
时间轴 风吹来的那片云   校对&总监 草草
熄灯
Lights out!
不要停
Keep it moving!
不得出列
Stay in line!
立定
Stop!
犯人戈登  请出列
Prisoner Gordon, step out of line
保持安静
and remain silent.
走起来
Let's move!
几周来你都没惹什么麻烦  戈登
Several weeks with no incidents, Gordon.
不错啊
I'm impressed.
我没想到  据说
Not what I expected. Word was you
你是个惹事精
were a troublemaker.
我只是想好好服刑
I just want to do my time.
该转移你了
Well, it's time to move you.
去哪里
Where to?
F区  "世界的尽头"
F Wing. "World's End."
普通囚区
General population.
你应该不会很惊讶
This should not come as a surprise to you.
保护性监禁只是暂时的特权
Protective custody is just a temporary privilege,
不适用于你那么长的刑期
one which can't be sustained for a sentence as long as yours.
除非你正在等待上诉
Perhaps you have an appeal pending,
那样的话  我可以延长这个安排
in which case I can prolong this arrangement.
你一定挺难受的吧
That's got to sting just a little, no?
你的人都抛弃了你
Your people seem to have abandoned you.
被判犯下谋杀罪有其坏处
Being convicted for murder has its downsides.
不要烦恼
Don't fret so.
你在F区肯定能见到许多老相识
I'm sure you'll see a lot of familiar faces over in F Wing.
许多人还是你自己逮捕的
Many of which you arrested yourself.
报复时间到了
It's payback time!
一记倒挂金钩
Here comes the flying scissor kick!
那不是我的吗
That one wasn't mine?
如果你能证明自己合群
If you show yourself to be a team player,
一切皆有可能
anything's possible.
你合群吗  戈登
Are you a team player, Gordon?
太棒了
I love it.
我忘了传达我...
And I forgot to pass on my...
好友的问候了
good friend's regard.
前局长洛布向你问好
Ex-Commissioner Loeb says hi.
遵守规则  或许你还能活下来
Follow the rules, and perhaps you'll survive.
违反规则  你肯定活不下来
Break them, and you most certainly won't.
所以这一区叫做"世界的尽头"
It's why they call this wing World's End.
对这里大多数人来说  这里就是尽头
For most here, it's exactly that, the end.
唯一的出路
Only way out:
假释或被装进尸袋
parole or a body bag.
从没有人获准假释
And nobody gets parole.
哥谭
第二季  第十六集
是真的  我发誓
It's true. I swear it.
我看得一清二楚  一个鬼魂
Clear as day-- a ghost.
是一个穿着黑长裙的苍白的老女人
She was this pale old woman in a long black dress.
就像你离我那么近
She was this close.
你当时什么反应
What did you do?
我尖叫着跑开了  还用说吗
Oh, I ran away screaming, of course.
你相信有鬼吗  奥斯瓦尔德
Oh, do you believe in ghosts, Oswald?
我相信
Yes, I do.
我见过
I've seen them.
这栋房子里有好几个呢
This house has several of them.
但别担心  它们都挺友好的
But don't worry, they're all quite friendly.
别听他胡说  这里没有鬼
Don't listen to him. There are no ghosts here.
这里是有鬼的
Oh, there's ghosts, all right.
这房子是我爷爷建的
This house was built by my grandfather.
他死在这儿的
He died here.
他妻子和他两个姐妹也是在楼上过世的
His wife and two sisters also passed away upstairs.
还有我可怜的父母
And my poor dear parents.
没错
Yes,
好多鬼
many ghosts.
你俩是怎么认识的
How did you meet?
那是个无聊的故事  真的
That's a boring story, really.
让我来说吧  亲爱的
No, let me tell it, dear.
我母亲去世后
After my mother died,
我在这房子里独自待了好几个月
I sat alone in this house for months.
事实上  我几乎不下床
Barely got out of bed, in fact.
最终  我找到了一间离这里不远的餐厅
Finally, I found a diner, not too far from here.
我每天同一时间去那里  点同样的东西
I'd go there every day at the same time, order the same thing.
鸡汤和苏打水
Chicken soup and a seltzer.
格蕾丝是我的服务员
Grace was my waitress,
我越来越喜欢她
and I grew very fond of her.
她和我讲了她两个可怜孩子的事
She told me of her two poor children,
萨莎和查尔斯
Sasha and Charles,
讲他们如何受他们父亲的虐待
and how they suffered at the hands of their abusive father.
我必须帮她  我向她提供庇护
I had to help. I offered her refuge,
她接受了
and she accepted.
于是这栋房子里再次有了欢声笑语
And this house heard laughter once again.
然后一切就顺其自然了
Then one thing led to another.
爱情萌发了
Love blossomed.
就成了如今这样
And here we are.
但你是我唯一的血亲  奥斯瓦尔德
But you are my only true blood relative, Oswald.
我的小可怜
Oh, my poor dear.
你伤到了吗
Are you hurt at all?
没有  没有  我没事
No, no. I'm-I'm fine.
笨手笨脚的
Clumsy girl.
敬家庭
To family.
-家庭  -敬家庭
- Family. - To family.
敬家庭
To family.
丹特  他们把他转到普通囚区了
Dent, they got him in general population now,
F区  你知道那意味着什么吗
F Wing. You know what that means?
我们送进去的人都关在那里
Everyone we've ever put away is in there!
别老是这句话  你总会有办法的
Stop saying that! There's always something you can do.
重审
A retrial.
或是让他转狱也行  老天啊
Or have him transferred to another prison, for God's sake.
你就继续这么做吧
You know what, just keep doing what you always do,
什么都不做
which is nothing!
爱德
Ed.
真凶不知在哪里
He's wasting away in that place
吃着甜甜圈  逍遥快活
while the real killer's out there somewhere,
他却在那里日渐憔悴
eating donuts and getting laid.
真凶
The real killer?
凶器上的指纹
The fingerprints on the murder weapon...
吉姆是清白的
Jim is innocent.
他没杀平克尼
He didn't kill Pinkney.
如果是真的话
Well, gee, um, that's... unfair
那真不公平
if that's true.
你打算怎么做
What are you gonna do about it?
我知道就好了
I wish I knew.
我的健康状况不允许我喝酒
My health forbids me from drinking,
但至少我能看着你享用这瓶雪利酒
but at least I can watch you enjoy this sherry.
这是我父亲生前最爱喝的酒
It was my father's favorite.
那是他吗
Is that him?
不  那是我曾祖父曼弗雷德
No, that's my great-grandfather Manfred.
很多年前  他在哥谭
He started a small tailor's shop
开了一家小裁缝店
in Gotham many, many years ago.
为城市精英制作西装
Made suits for the city's elite.
我父亲像他的哥哥们那样做了学徒
My father became an apprentice like every son before him.
-你也做了学徒吗  -是的
- You were an apprentice, too? - I was.
还相当有天赋呢
Had rather a flare for it.
可惜没那个命
But it was not to be.
我父亲病倒之后
When my father succumbed to illness,
我母亲把我留在身边
my mother held me close to her.
让我在家接受教育
Homeschooled me.
她认为有必要保护我
She felt a need to protect me
不受到城市里的诱惑
from the temptations of the city.
这段时间以来  我不敢问你母亲的事
All this time, I've been afraid to ask about your mother.
我很抱歉我抛弃了她
I'm so sorry I abandoned her.
如果当初我知道我还抛弃了你
Had I known I was also abandoning you...
上帝啊
Dear God,
我真是个胆小的笨蛋
such a cowardly fool.
她这辈子过得快乐吗
Did she have a happy life?
不
No.
不快乐
Not a happy life.
但是还不错
But a good one.
她从未伤害过任何人
She never hurt a soul.
我有时不太孝顺
I was not always a good son,
但她从未责备过我
and she never spoke a word of reproach.
有时不孝顺
Not always a good son?
我觉得很难相信呢
I find that hard to credit.
像你这么体面的年轻人
An nice young man like you?
相信我
Believe me.
我干过很多坏事
I've done bad things.
我们都有罪  孩子
We're all sinners, my boy.
你该吃药了  亲爱的
It's time for your medicine, my love.
谢谢
Thank you.
医生开的治心脏的药
Doctor gave them to me for my heart.
小心驶得万年船
Better safe than sorry.
以利亚·范·达尔
每日口服一片
薄荷糖
以利亚·范·达尔
每日口服一片
薄荷糖
以利亚·范·达尔
每日口服一片
有人探视  戈登先生
You have a visitor, Mr. Gordon.
这边请
This way, please.
不  我不要回禁闭室
No, I'm not going back to the hole!
他保证过的
He promised!
-是典狱长要转移你的  -什么
- The warden's the one who's moving you. - What?!
说好的可不是这样
This wasn't our agreement!
不  你听着  这不公平
No, you listen! This isn't fair!
我买了这间牢房  这是我的
I paid for this cell! This is mine!
你听到了吗
You hear me?!
这边请
This way, please.
这里交易还挺多的
A lot of business going on.
典狱长能分一杯羹吗
The warden get a cut?
快到了
Almost there.
我要这童子军周末前死掉
I want the Boy Scout dead by week's end.
哎哟
Damn.
你气色不错啊  兄弟
You look good, brother.
这地方挺适合你的
This place agrees with you.
也许我也该进来
Maybe I'll check in.
减几斤肉
Lose a few pounds, hmm?
弄个酷文身
Get a cool tat.
你不非得来看我的
You don't need to check up on me.
你开玩笑呢
Are you kidding?
看到你的笑脸是我一周里最开心的事了
Highlight of my week to see your smiling face.
听着  我和丹特谈过了
Look, I spoke to Dent.
他有意重新开启案子
He's looking into reopening the case.
但你不能惹事
But you got to keep your nose clean.
千万别因为管不住脾气
Last thing you can do is do more time
而被加刑  好吗
'cause you lost your temper, all right?
应该没那么难
Ah, shouldn't be that hard.
这里的人看起来都挺和气的
Everyone seems really nice around here.
我在找企鹅
I'm looking for Penguin.
看看他有什么想说的没
See what he's got to say.
他躲在什么地方避风头了  但别担心
He's laying low someplace, but don't worry.
我会找到他的
I'll find him.
小莱怎样了
How's Lee?
她一直在给我写信
Been writing to me a lot.
几周前突然不再来信了
The letters stopped a few weeks ago.
知道为什么吗
Know why?
我真不想做告诉你这消息的人
I didn't want to be the one to tell you this.
告诉我什么
Tell me what?
小莱的孩子没了  吉姆
Lee lost the baby, Jim.
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
她怎样了
How is she?
我不知道
I-I don't know.
她应该还好
I think she's fine.
她搬去南部了
She moved down south.
之后就再没人有她的消息了
No one's heard from her since.
不要让这事击溃你
Hey, don't let this beat you.
见到你很高兴  哈维
It's good to see you, Harv.
吉姆  我会救你出去的  我保证
Jim, I'm gonna get you out of here, I promise.
吉姆  别让这事击溃你
Jim, don't let this break you!
不要放弃希望
Don't give up hope.
吉姆  吉姆
Jim! Jim!
你要去哪  猪头
Where you going, pig?
我弟弟去年和几个人一起抢银行来着
My little brother ran with a crew that pulled off a few bank jobs last year.
报纸上管他们叫红头罩帮
Papers called them the Red Hood Gang?
还记得吗
Remember them?
你一枪打爆了我弟弟的头
You put a bullet in my brother's head.
这是谁呀
Now, who's this?
我让外面的朋友去看看她好不好
How about I have my friends on the outside pay her a visit?
让她知道她错过了什么
Show her what she's been missing?
真惨
Oh, snap!
各位  冷静
Guys, cool it!
冷静一下
Cool it, huh?
别冲动
Peace, peace.
别插手
Don't.
没事的  戈登先生
It's all right, Mr. Gordon.
交给我吧  好了  各位
I got this. Now, come on now, guys.
大家都深呼吸一下
Let's just take a deep breath...
各回各的牢房
Get back to your cells!
你
You!
跪在原地
Assume the position now.
马上
Now!
退后  退后
Back it up! Back it up!
带犯人维弗去禁闭室
Take inmate Weaver to the hole.
这两个送去医务室
And these two to the infirmary.
起来  起来
Get up. Get up!
走吧  你听到长官的话了
Let's go. You heard him.
-父亲  -怎么
- Father? - What?
是谁
Who?
没事的  你只是在梦游
It's okay. You were sleepwalking.
确实
Oh, I was.
这是我父亲的办公室
My father's office.
来  我给你搬把椅子吧
Here, let me, let me get you a chair?
不用  扶我回床上去吧  好吗
No, help me back to bed, won't you?
好
Of course.
利伐沙班
以利亚·范·达尔
都是控制病情的药
They're for my condition.
心脏病吗
Your heart?
我心脏上有个洞
I have a hole in it.
据说还在不断扩大
It keeps getting bigger apparently.
我觉得是我的心魔在吞噬它
I think my demons are feeding on it.
你有心魔吗
You have demons?
很不幸  我有
Sadly, I do.
恐怕你也有
You, too, I fear.
我有很多事没告诉你
There's so much I haven't told you.
很多让我羞愧的事
So much that I'm ashamed of.
我以前是个罪犯
I was a criminal.
我造了
I've done...
很多孽
horrible things.
伤害别人
Hurt people,
耍心机  满口谎言
manipulated, lied.
为了谋权
For power,
为了复仇
for revenge.
我杀过人  父亲
I've killed people, Father.
我们的生活始于我在墓地遇见你的那一刻
Our lives together started the moment I met you at the cemetery.
我不在乎你的过去
Nothing before that concerns me.
我原谅你过去所有的罪过
I forgive you for all your past transgressions.
别再纠结过去
Be free of them
在这里好好生活
and live here in peace.
我们叫他们知道厉害了
We showed them, huh?
听我说  不管你是谁
Look, uh, whatever your name is...
帕克
Puck-- well,
其实是彼得
Peter actually,
但大家都叫我帕克
but people call me Puck.
离我远点  好吗
Stay away from me, okay?
我不需要你的帮助
I don't need your help.
那可不行
Can't do that,
戈登警探
Detective Gordon.
我不再是警探了
I'm not a detective anymore.
我知道
Oh, I know.
你比警探要厉害
You're way more than that.
你是个真正的英雄
You're a true hero.
两年前
Two winters ago,
我妹妹被儿童绑架犯抓走了
my little sister was abducted by child snatchers.
她被掳走了三天
Three days she was gone.
是你找到了她  抓到了那群人渣
And then you found her and-and busted the scum that took her.
你救了她  还救过很多人
You saved her life and dozens of others.
这就是真英雄的作为
Right there, that's a true hero.
我只是尽职而已
Just doing my job.
不  先生
No, sir.
你怎么进来的
What are you in for?
因为一个姑娘
A girl.
一个漂亮的姑娘
Beautiful girl.
我约她出来  她同意了
I asked her out and she said yes.
她很有格调
And she was classy.
我不能让她坐公交
I couldn't make her take the bus
所以我偷了辆车
so I snatched a car.
其实是借
Well, borrowed it.
我打算还回去的
I was gonna take it back.
警察不相信我
Cops didn't believe me,
所以我就进来了
so here I am.
判了你几年
What they give you?
六年
Six years.
不少啊
Steep.
我可没法抱怨
Hey, I can't complain.
我犯法了
I broke the law, right?
法律就是法律
The law is the law.
我可不会像我爷爷一样
I'm not gonna be like my grandfather.
他死在了这里
He died in here.
过了一段时间后就再不许我和父亲来看他了
And wouldn't let me and my father visit him after a while.
但我们后来还是来了
But finally we did.
最后一次见他时
Last time I saw him,
他不一样了
he was different.
都认不出来了
Didn't recognize him.
我不会落得那种下场
That's not gonna happen to me.
不  先生  我不会死在这里
No, sir, I won't die in here.
那就离我远一点
Then stay away from me.
这俩犯人怎么还在这里
What are these prisoners still doing here?
马上带他们回各自的牢房
Get them to their cells immediately.
盯紧这家伙
And watch this one.
他刚失去了孩子
He just lost a child.
这让他很愤怒
Makes him mad.
没错
That's right.
我耳听四路
I hear everything.
眼观八方
I see everything.
你知道的一切
Everything you know,
我都知道
I know.
我知道一件你不知道的事
I know something you don't know.
是吗  什么事
Yeah, what's that?
我知道你是怎样的人
I know what kind of man you are.
把他带走
Get him out of here.
快点
Now.
赢了
Gin.
以利亚
Elijah?
坐稳了
Brace yourself.
恐怕我们有一些坏消息
I'm afraid we have some bad news.
天啊
Oh, dear.
查尔斯今天去了公共图书馆
Charles was at the public library today.
为我正在写的小说搜集资料
Research for the novel I'm writing.
我当时在看一些旧报纸
I was reading some old newspapers,
发现了一件令人震惊的事
and I made an alarming discovery.
亲爱的
My dear,
奥斯瓦尔德才不像他说的那么体面
Oswald is not the nice young man he says he is.
如果我们不是那么与世隔绝
If we didn't lead such sheltered lives here,
就会知道全世界都知道的真相了
we would know what the whole world knows.
他是一名臭名昭著的罪犯
He's a notorious criminal.
我们一直在庇护
We've been sheltering
一名杀人犯
a killer.
企鹅被抓
我们都可能在自己的床上被人奸杀
We could have all been raped and murdered in our beds.
奸杀
Raped and murdered.
他们叫你企鹅
They call you the Penguin?
说句公道话...
To be fair...
我从没强奸过谁
...I never raped anybody.
那真是上天保佑  是不是
Oh, well, that's a mercy, now, isn't it?
我儿子把他的过去告诉我了
My son told me about his past.
他只是没说他有多出名
He just didn't tell me how famous he was.
你太谦虚了  儿子
You're too modest, son.
以利亚
Elijah...
我们家里住个暴力罪犯
a violent criminal in our house?
格蕾丝  放松
Grace, relax,
他已经变了
he's changed.
获得救赎了
Redeemed.
你已经不是这种人了  是吧
You're not this man anymore, are you?
不是了  先生
Oh, no, sir.
你怎么知道他不是了
But how... h-how do you know? How do you know he's not?
我审视了他的灵魂
I've looked into his soul.
我看到了他美丽的心灵
I've seen his beautiful heart.
"衣冠楚楚的黑社会头头"
"The Dapper Gangland Kingpin."
现在怎么办
What now?
B计划
Plan B.
B计划是什么
What's plan B?
你啊  亲爱的
You are, my dear.
早上好
Good morning.
我想跟你独处一会儿  企鹅先生
I was hoping to spend a little time with you, Mr. Penguin.
好吧  但是
Okay. But, um,
请叫我奥斯瓦尔德
uh, please, call me Oswald.
我已经不是那个人了
I-I'm not that man anymore.
就没剩下一点企鹅的影子吗
There isn't a little bit of Penguin left?
一点坏小子
A little bad boy?
没有了
No.
我内心有个坏女孩呢
I got a little bad girl in me.
不管你对那老头子有什么打算  我想加入
Whatever you've got planned for the old man, I want in.
-加入  -我们可以有很大成就
- In? - We could do great things, you and me.
或许吧  我...
I suppose. I hadn't...
如果我们合作
If you and me work together,
我们可以拥有一切
we could have it all.
我们可以把我妈妈和弟弟挤走
We could squeeze my mom and brother out.
我们为什么要那么做
Why would we do that?
我不知道
I don't know.
或许我们就是一对儿疯狂乱套的孩子
I guess we're just a couple of crazy mixed up kids.
控制点自己  女人
Restrain yourself, woman.
我基本上是你哥哥了
I'm your practically your brother.
你在想什么啊
What are you thinking?
他没上钩
He didn't bite.
要我去试试吗
Should I try?
不  我觉得他不是装的
No. I don't think he's faking.
我觉得是傻
I think he's kind of simple.
戈登
Gordon.
戈登  小心点
Gordon. Watch yourself.
维弗马上要从禁闭室出来了
Weaver's coming out the hole. Now.
这就出来了
Already?
这里没什么事是合情合理的
Nothing happens around here like it's supposed to.
你的死期要到了  戈登
Your day's coming, Gordon.
你死定了
You're a dead man!
看看你男朋友吧
Take a look at your boyfriend over there.
帕克
Puck!
现在还有谁会帮你  猪头
Who's gonna help you now, pig?
你喜欢那样吗  戈登
Yeah, you like that, Gordon?
别管了
Let it go.
别延长你的刑期
Don't extend your sentence.
吉姆没杀那孩子  我们都知道
Jim didn't kill that kid. We all know it.
问题是  是谁杀的
Thing is, who did?
是谁陷害了他
I mean, who'd set him up that way?
我不知道他还能在
I just don't know how much longer
那地方支撑多久
he can stay alive in that place.
我是想求你帮忙
I guess I'm asking for your help.
真有趣
Funny, huh?
你完全有权利叫我滚蛋
You have every right to tell me to go to hell.
但是我
But I...
我已经没别人可以求助了
I got no one else to turn to.
哈维
You know, Harvey...
在室内戴帽子是很没礼貌的
it's very rude to wear a hat indoors.
喜欢这面料吗  是意大利的
You like the fabric? It's Italian.
我好喜欢
I love it.
一个人可以靠衣着表现出自己很多方面
A man can say so much about himself by what he wears.
我太赞同了
I couldn't agree more.
我为当今穿衣随便的年轻人难过
I weep for today's casual youth.
我很高兴你提议我们做这个
I'm so glad you suggested we do this.
我好久没做了
It's been so long.
你没事吧
Are you all right?
父亲
Father?
救命
Help!
谁去叫医生
Have someone call for an ambulance!
格蕾丝  救命  格蕾丝
Grace! Help! Help, Grace!
你们把以利亚怎么了
What did you do to Elijah?
-没怎么啊  -救命
- Nothing. - Help!
就来  亲爱的
Coming, my dear.
把这里收拾好
Clean up this mess
叫医生来
and call the doctor.
走开
Go on.
挺卖力啊
Hard at it, I see.
谢谢你恢复我的工作
Thanks for getting me my old job back.
你朋友帕克被打得不轻
Your friend Puck is pretty banged up.
如果你去医务室看他  或许对他有好处
Might do him some good if you were to come see him in the infirmary.
算了吧
Yeah, no.
我不是他的朋友
I'm not his friend.
他认为你是
He thinks you are.
那孩子会死在这里的
The kid's gonna die in here,
迟早的事
one way or another.
我们很快完事
We'll be quick.
你怎么样
How you holding up?
挺好
Cool.
他们说我有个血块还是什么的
They-they said I have a clot or something.
我就是觉得晕
I just feel seasick.
谢谢你来看我
Thanks for coming to see me.
我很高兴
Means a lot.
他们肯定会好好照顾你的
I'm sure they'll take good care of you in here.
你撑住
You hang in there, huh?
听着
Listen...
别放弃希望
...don't give up hope.
我理解你的难过
I feel your sadness.
真的  但是
I do, but...
你得选择生活
you got to choose life, you know?
好吧
Okay.
选择生活
Choose life.
好
Good.
听着  孩子
Listen, kid, uh...
等你好起来了  你得吸取教训
when you get better, you learn the lesson here
离我远远的
and you stay the hell away from me.
我不是英雄  也不是你的朋友
I'm not a hero and I'm not your friend.
我就是个囚犯
I'm just a convict.
今晚是电影之夜
Tonight's movie night.
所有人都聚在大堂  还关着灯
Everyone in the main hall together with the lights off.
做好准备
Be ready.
准备什么
For what?
做好准备就是了
Just be ready.
他的情况恶化了
His condition has gotten worse.
那个洞扩大了
The hole has gotten bigger
又出现了感染
and now there's an infection.
我给了他抗生素  能帮他补水
I've given him antibiotics and rehydrated him,
但恐怕用处不大
but I fear it will have little consequence.
他该料理后事了
It's time for him to get his affairs in order.
他可能时日无多了
He may not have long.
我去让他们给你做碗鸡汤
I'm going to have them make you some nice chicken soup.
你需要力气
You need your strength.
多谢你了
How kind.
过来  孩子
Come here, my boy.
别听医生的  儿子
Don't listen to doctors, son.
我曾那么多次证明他们错了  都数不过来了
I've proved them wrong so many times I've lost count.
你和我还能共度很多年
You and I will have many more years to spend together.
相信我
Trust me.
但或许我们该找律师来谈谈  亲爱的
But perhaps we should speak with my lawyer, dear.
我有些事想跟他商谈
I have some things I'd like to go over with him.
这几周来  发生了很多改变
So much has changed these past weeks.
当然了
Of course.
我会叫他来的
I'll have him stop by.
坐下
Sit down.
安静
Settle.
嗯
Right.
他叫律师了
He's called for his lawyer.
-他要修改遗嘱吗  -是的
- He's going to change his will? - Yes.
等他死了  科波特就会得到应属于我们的
And when he dies, Cobblepot will get what's rightfully ours.
我认识那老头子时  他憔悴不堪
That old man was a shriveled-up wreck when I met him.
是我让他重获青春  是我让他重焕生机
I made him feel young again. I brought him back to life.
这只臭老鼠又做过什么
And what has this gutter rodent done?
玩破棋盘游戏
Played stupid board games
念叨他可怜的母亲
and whined about his wretched mother.
那只害虫必须走
That vermin has to go.
但他喜欢这里
But he likes it here.
我们要怎么说服他离开
How can we persuade him to go?
老鼠要怎么除掉呢
How do you get rid of rats?
-老鼠胶吗  -不是  傻帽
- Glue traps? - No, silly.
大家伙
Hello. Hello.
父亲好多了  但他在休息
Father is feeling much better, but he is resting,
他今晚就不来了
so he will not be joining us tonight.
没事
Well, that's fine.
我们吃饭吧
Let's eat, hmm?
谢谢
Thank you.
我是只漂亮的苍蝇  看啊
I'm a pretty fly. Look, everybody.
嗯  看啊  大家伙
Yeah! Come on, everybody.
表演结束了
Yo, show's over.
趴下
Yo, get down!
你干什么呢  他是我的
What are you doing? He's mine!
他是我的
He's mine!
别起来
Stay down!
你死了  明白吗
You're dead. You understand?
明白吗
You understand?!
你死了  猪头
You're dead, pig.
我们需要个尸袋
We're gonna need a body bag.
布洛克
Bullock?
你怎么在这儿
What the hell are you doing here?
你觉得我们是在做什么
What's it look like we're doing?
我们要把你弄出去  来吧  走吧
We're getting you out of here. Come on, let's go.
假血  可伸缩刀  居然真成功了
Fake blood, retractable knife-- can't believe it worked.
等等  等等
Wait. Wait.
哈维  如果我就该待在这里呢
Harvey, what if this is where I'm supposed to be?
-什么  快走  -布洛克
- What?! Let's go! - Bullock...
你确定吗
You sure?
你嗑药了吗  很多好人为你
Are you tripping? A lot of good men put their butts
冒了极大风险  我  他  法尔科内阁下
on a live rail for you-- me, him, Don freaking Falcone.
而杀了平克尼的人现在还逍遥法外
While walking around somewhere is the guy that killed Pinkney,
他陷害了你  破坏了你的家庭
framed you and destroyed your family.
他逍遥法外  而你就站在那儿
He's walking around while you're standing there
难过迷茫
all blue and misty.
去你的自怨自艾  赶紧走吧
Well, screw your self-pity and let's go!
阿门
Amen.
好吧
All right.
但我还需要你们帮个忙
But I need one more favor.
谁啊
Hello?
戈登警探
Detective Gordon?
我们走
We're out of here.
你得尽量快  尽量轻地跟我们走
I need you to move as quickly and quietly as you can.
-逃跑吗  -是的
- You mean, like, escaping? - Like that.
-但那是违法的  -是啊
- But that's against the law. - Yeah.
你说了  选择生活
Like you said, choose life.
我早说的  是吧
Told you, didn't I?
不管你怎么想  你就是个英雄
Whether you like it or not, you're a hero.
犯人戈登
Prisoner Gordon.
你不是死了吗
You're supposed to be dead.
我跟你一样意外
I'm as surprised as you are.
你是怎么活过来的
What brought you back to life?
-朋友  -朋友
- Friends. - Friends.
有朋友真好
It's good to have friends.
但你需要朋友的时候他们又不见了  是吧
But where are they when you need 'em, huh? Where...?
感觉太爽了
Man, that felt good.
抱歉把你卷进来
Sorry I got you into all this.
开什么玩笑  从没觉得这么带劲过
Are you kidding? Never felt more alive.
狠狠地揍我  弄得像点
Now, hit me hard, make it look good.
别揍牙  我才修过
Just don't touch the teeth. I just had 'em fixed.
看你母亲啊  她当时多年轻
Look at your mother-- she was so young.
奥斯瓦尔德
Oswald.
谢谢你  格蕾丝
Thank you so much, Grace.
我骗了你  儿子
I lied to you, son.
我父亲并没有身体疾病
My father was never physically ill.
他是深陷忧郁症
He only suffered a deep melancholy.
他内心充满黑暗的冲动
He was plagued by dark impulses,
暴力的邪恶念头
evil thoughts of violence.
母亲说  他家族很多人都有这个毛病
Mother said many in his family had the same affliction.
我记得那枪声
I remember the sound of the gunshot.
我当时在他房间外
I was outside his room.
我尖叫着让母亲去拿钥匙
I screamed for my mother to get the key.
我看到他手上尚有余温的枪
I saw the warm gun in his hand.
鲜血
The blood.
他的脸
His face.
母亲叫我永远别提起
Mother said never to talk about it.
葬礼后数年  我们一直足不出户
For years after the funeral, we never left the house.
我不想假装理解我父亲受的折磨
I don't pretend to understand my father's torment.
但或许你理解
But I think perhaps you do.
我替你难过
I feel for you,
我求你  儿子
and I beg of you, my son.
永远别像他那样向痛苦屈服
Never give in to the pain as he did.
有人爱你
You are loved,
你不是一个人
and you are not alone.
太阳明天还会升起
And the sun will come up tomorrow.
谢谢你  父亲
Thank you, Father.
我想喝一杯
Now I feel like a drink.
但你的身体不要紧吗
But your health?
管他呢
To hell with that.
我希望你拥有一切  儿子
I want you to have it all, my son.
这栋房子  和里面的一切
This house and all that's in it.
都保持原样
Keep it just the way it is,
一件历史  我们的历史
a piece of history, our history.
哥谭的历史
Gotham's history.
明天一早  我就会让律师起草文件
First thing tomorrow, I'll have my lawyers draw it up.
父亲
Father?
-不  -以利亚
- Oh, no! - Elijah!
他喝了那个吗
Did he... did he drink that?
-是啊  -为什么
- Yes. - Why? Why?
他不该喝的  萨莎
He's not supposed to. Sasha,
叫救护车
call an ambulance. Call an am...
撑住  父亲
Stay with us, Father.
救护车就到了
Help is on the way.
不
No!
我们逃出来了  伙计
We made it, buddy.
等着
Wait here.
法尔科内阁下在黑门监狱有的是人
Don Falcone had all the contacts inside of Blackgate.
是他策划了整件事
He made this whole thing happen.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我恐怕无以为报
I'm not sure I can ever repay you.
不必
It won't be necessary.
我乐意帮助老朋友
I'm happy to help an old friend.
现在怎么办
What now?
你问我吗
You're asking me?
两小时前我还是个死人呢
Two hours ago, I was a dead man.
我有人能帮你出国
I have people that will get you out of the country.
也可以在哥谭给你安排个安全的住处
Or I can arrange a safe place for you in Gotham.
你自己选
Your choice.
你想怎么办
What do you want to do?
我想去找小莱
I want to go find Lee.
但那就得先洗清我的罪名
But to do that, I have to clear my name.
那我就得回哥谭
And to do that, I have to go back to Gotham.
那么你有答案了
So there's your answer.
我心里一部分想逃
Part of me says, run.
我呼吸到了新鲜空气
I'm breathing fresh air.
我不想再回去了
I can't go back inside.
如果你逃
If you run,
你就得一直跑下去
you've got to keep running.
这有些人可以承受
Some people can live with that.
你是个斗士  吉姆
You're a fighter, Jim.
你被打趴了
You got knocked down.
你会一直趴着吗
Do you stay down?
还是重新站起来
Or do you get back up?
你觉得呢  小子
What do you think, kid?
帕克
Puck?
不不  我们都出来了  别这样
No. No, we made it. Come on.
别这样啊
Come on. No. Come on!
别放弃
Don't give up!
帕克
Puck?
他死了
He's gone.
吉姆  他死了
Jim, he's gone.